Hi there.
Welcome to this video
where we are going to learn about
the attacker's
perspective in cybersecurity.
The goal of the video is
to emphasize the existing risks posed
by some unfriendly actors,
called attackers in cyberspace.
In the video, firstly,
we will discuss what the attacker is.
Then we will distinguish
the common types of attackers
and examine their motivations
for engaging in malicious,
deliberately harmful activity
in the digital environment.
According to the dictionary,
the adversary is someone
who opposes or resists.
It is an enemy or an opponent.
A more specific term attacker
identifies someone who carries out
harmful actions
in the cybersecurity field.
An attacker is an individual or entity
that causes problems for regular users
and companies to perform
tasks and duties in the digital space.
The attacker can be
a person, group, or organization
that conducts malicious activities
against digital resources.
Typically, we refer to such
a person as an attacker
due to their aggressive or active pose.
Cybersecurity professionals
distinguish various types of attackers
and link them to specific motivations.
Today, we will learn about
some of the most common types
you could meet or hear about
when doing your daily activities.
Insiders, hacktivists, script kiddies,
nation state actors, and cyber criminals.
Let us start with insiders.
An insider is someone who knows
information available within
a group due to being part of that group.
We are all insiders of various groups.
Typically, it is a regular thing.
However, in cybersecurity,
the concept of an insider threat
refers to an insider
who not only possesses knowledge,
but also utilizes it in a manner
that leads to negative consequences
for the group or specific individuals.
For example, let us assume that you share
your password for the gaming
platform with your best friend.
The friend wants to impress
some older schoolchildren
and gives them your password.
These older children access
your account and take control of it.
Your friend is an insider,
but the actions led
to some negative consequences
from your perspective.
That is why we should all
be careful when sharing personal data.
Another type of attacker is hacktivists.
The concept of a hacktivist is constructed
from two words: hacker and activist.
A hacker is a person who knows a lot
about computers and computer systems.
This person utilizes their
knowledge and skills to gain access
to systems, to steal the data
or disturb those systems.
It is a cyber hooligan.
An activist is a person
who stands up for a cause they believe in.
A hacktivist uses
their hacking skills to send a message,
usually about something
they perceive as unfair in the world.
For example, a hacktivist who loves nature
could disrupt the website of a company
that cuts down trees
in the forest and sells timber.
Script kiddies make another
type of adversary actor.
Script kiddies possess
some skills and knowledge
that enable them to break into
or disturb computer systems.
However, they lack
the necessary knowledge and skills
to comprehend
the implications of their actions.
Typically, script kiddies
are eager to discover
software and run or test it,
sometimes to show off.
For example, your friend could use
a specialized application to run at school
and potentially disrupt
the entire school's computer network.
If your friend has no idea
how everything is developed
and why the software
behaves in a certain way,
it means we have some script kiddies around.
Cyber criminals are adversary actors
or attackers with larger goals
than just disrupting the school's
computer network or public services.
Cyber criminals are highly ambitious
and seek financial or reputational gain.
Do you have a supermarket around
where you go from time to time?
The targets of cyber criminals
could target payment systems,
cash registers and some
specialized logistics systems.
Cyber criminals could attempt
to steal data about the credit cards
used in these systems.
In the news, you might have heard
about state sponsored actors.
It is not a secret that among
more than 200 countries globally,
there are alliances and opposing parties.
Among the alliances,
there are competitions
in innovations
and disagreements over values.
Thus, state sponsor some hacker groups
to sabotage events
or to engage in espionage,
aiming to get data or specific knowledge
related to secret information.
Now you know several types of adversaries
and their motivation
to perform adversarial actions.
Could you think of
one sentence to describe each
of the adversary actors
listed in the slide?
Let us take a moment to think.
Was it enough time to find the
proper words in trying to distinguish all types?
One more thing to mention. When your
computer freezes or your phone stops working.
It does not mean
that you have been attacked.
To attribute the incident
to a particular adversary
an investigation is needed.
Thank you for watching.
Do not forget to watch
other videos in our series.